Cleveland Abbe Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Cleveland Abbe Papers 1850-1954 (bulk 1850-1916)
MSS10025
Abbe, Cleveland, 1838-1916
9,500 items 31 containers plus 3 oversize 12.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Astronomer and meteorologist. Correspondence, diaries, and other papers relating mainly to Abbe's career with the Weather Service of the Army Signal Corps, his participation in the West African Eclipse Expedition (1880s), and his career in the United States Weather Bureau.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Abbe, Cleveland, 1838-1916.; Abbe, Robert, 1851-1928--Correspondence.; Abbey family.; Bickmore, Albert S. (Albert Smith), 1839-1914--Correspondence.; Coffin, James H. (James Henry), 1806-1873--Correspondence.; Ferrel, William, 1817-1891--Correspondence.; Gibbs, Wolcott, 1822-1908--Correspondence.; Gould, Benjamin Apthorp, 1824-1896--Correspondence.; Hall, Asaph, 1829-1907--Correspondence.; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878--Correspondence.; Langley, S. P. (Samuel Pierpont), 1834-1906--Correspondence.; Newcomb, Simon, 1835-1909--Correspondence.; Packard, A. S. (Alpheus Spring), 1839-1905--Correspondence.; Peirce, Benjamin, 1809-1880--Correspondence.; Rutherford, Lewis M.--Correspondence.; Safford, Truman Henry, 1836-1901--Correspondence.; Searle, G. M. (George Mary), 1839-1918--Correspondence.; Struve, Otto, 1819-1905--Correspondence.; Watson, James C. (James Craig), 1838-1880--Correspondence.
Organizations
Glavnai︠a︡ astronomicheskai︠a︡ observatorii︠a︡ (Pulkovo, Russia); United States Coast Survey.; United States. Army. Signal Corps.; United States. Weather Bureau.
Subjects
Astronomical observatories--Russia (Federation)--Pulkovo.; Astronomy.; Eclipses.; Longitude.; Meteorology.; Scientific expeditions--Africa, West.; Weather--Maps.; Weather.
Occupations
Astronomers.; Meteorologists.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Cleveland Abbe, astronomer and meteorologist, were given to the Library of Congress by Abbe's granddaughter Petrena Abbe Shea in 1963. Additional material was transferred that year from the National Archives and Records Administration.
Additional Guides
The Abbe Papers are described in the Library of Congress Information Bulletin, vol. 22, no. 29 (22 July 1963), pages 357-358, and in Nathan Reingold, "A Good Place to Study Astronomy," Library of Congress Quarterly Journal of Current Acquisitions, vol. 20, no. 4 (September 1963), pages 211-217.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Cleveland Abbe are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1838, Dec. 2 Born, New York, N.Y.
1857 B.A., College of the City of New York, New York, N.Y.
1859-1860 Taught engineering at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Mich. Studied astronomy under Franz Brünnow
1860 M.A., College of the City of New York, New York, N.Y.
1861-1864 Assisted Benjamin Apthorp Gould on longitude determinations for the United States Coast Survey
1864-1866 Guest astronomer, Observatory of Pulkovo, Russia
1867-1868 Aid, United States Naval Observatory
1868-1873 Director, Cincinnati Observatory, Cincinnati, Ohio
1869 Began publishing daily weather reports for the Cincinnati Chamber of Commerce
1870 Married Frances Martha Neal (died 1908)
1871-1916 Meteorologist, United States Signal Corps and the United States Weather Bureau
1884-1916 Professor of meteorology, Columbian (George Washington) University, Washington, D.C.
1895-1916 Lecturer on meteorology, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md.
1906 Awarded the Franklin Medal by the American Philosophical Society
1909 Married Margaret Augusta Percival
1912 Awarded the Symons Memorial Gold Medal by the Royal Meteorological Society of London
1916 Awarded the Marcellus Hartley Medal by the National Academy of Sciences
1916, Oct. 24 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the American meteorologist Cleveland Abbe (1838-1916) span the years 1850-1954, with the bulk of the material dated up to 1916. The papers consist mainly of correspondence received by Abbe and a few copies of his replies and are organized into the following series: Diaries, General Correspondence, Family Correspondence and Related Papers, Subject File, Speech and Article File, and Printed Matter.
The General Correspondence contains many letters from the American astronomer Benjamin Apthorp Gould, whom Cleveland Abbe assisted at Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1861-1864, in the telegraphic longitude work of the United States Coast Survey. There are also numerous letters from Otto Struve, former director of the Nicholas Central Observatory of Pulkovo, near St. Petersburg, Russia, where Abbe spent two years, 1864-1866, as a guest astronomer. Other prominent correspondents include Albert S. Bickmore, James H. Coffin, William Ferrel, Wolcott Gibbs, Asaph Hall, Joseph Henry, S. P. Langley, Simon Newcomb, A. S. Packard, Benjamin Pierce, Lewis M. Rutherford, Truman Henry Safford, and James C. Watson. Abbe's career as meteorologist with the United States Signal Corps and with the United States Weather Bureau, which was organized under the Department of Agriculture, is also reflected in his correspondence.
The Family and Related Papers contain a sizeable number of letters received from members of his family, notably those from his brother Robert Abbe, an American surgeon who was one of the first in the United States to use radium in the treatment of cancer.
The Subject File contains papers relating to Abbe's activities following his return to the United States from Russia. In 1868, he became director of the Cincinnati Observatory, and his interest shifted from the field of astronomy to that of meteorology and the practical application of that science in preparing weather forecasts and issuing warnings of approaching storms. There are a number of the earliest maps that Abbe constructed in 1870 showing the current state of weather conditions over the country based on telegraphic reports of weather conditions in various locations throughout the nation. There are also copies of weather synopses and probabilities from 1872 that were issued in the forms of bulletins with the cooperation of the Cincinnati Chamber of Commerce, the first regular undertaking of this kind in America and prototype of the present weather service. The series also contains papers collected by Abbe relating to the Abbe family genealogy, a work that for nearly sixty years was his recreation and hobby.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in six series:
Diaries, 1862-1889
General Correspondence, 1850-1916
Family Correspondence and Related Papers, circa 1858-1954
Subject File, 1855-1884
Speech and Article File
Printed Matter
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm73010025
Container List
- Diaries, 1862-1889 (Box 1)
  Diaries.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1862-1870, 1889 (Box 1)
- General Correspondence, 1850-1916 (Box 2-9)
  Letters received and copies of letters sent, including letters sent by Cleveland Abbe to various members of the Abbe family.
  - 1850-1866, May 8 (Box 2)
  - 1866, May 11-1868, Aug. 31 (Box 3)
  - 1868, Sept. 2-1869, July 20 (Box 4)
  - 1869, July 21-1870, May 31 (Box 5)
  - 1870, June 6-1871, Dec. 27 (Box 6)
  - 1872, 17 Jan.-1877, 29 Oct. (Box 7)
  - 1878, Feb. 8-1893, June 26 (Box 8)
  - 1893, June 27-1916 (Box 9)
  - Undated (Box 9)
- Family Correspondence and Related Papers, circa 1858-1954 (Box 10-12)
  Correspondence and related items such as diaries, medical case notebooks, radium photographs, genealogical material, and the manuscript of Cleveland Abbe by Truman Abbe.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of family member.
  - Abbe, Charles (Box 10)
  - Abbe, Cleveland (1872-1934) (Box 10)
  - Abbe, Fanny (Box 10)
  - Abbe, George (Box 10)
  - Abbe, Robert (Box 10)
  - Abbe, Truman (Box 10)
  - Abbe, Truman (Box 11)
  - Abbe, Truman (Box 12)
  - Abbe, William C. (Box 12)
  - Hooper, Mary L. (Box 12)
- Subject File, 1855-1884 (Box 13-31)
  Genealogical material assembled by Abbe, biographical material, financial records, lecture notebooks, meteorological maps, charts, synopses and forecasts, photographs, holograph astronomical papers and notes, and memorabilia.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject or type of material.
  - Abbe family genealogy (Box 13-14)
  - Biographical material (Box 15)
  - Brown, Reginald C., papers (Box 16)
  - Financial papers (Box 16)
  - Financial papers (Box 17)
  - Lecture notebooks, circa 1860s (Box 17)
  - Meteorological data (statistics, barometric readings, and miscellaneous items), 1880-1884 (Box 18)
  - Photographs (Box 19-21)
  - Photographs (Box 22 (oversize))
  - Scientific papers (Box 23)
    - Astronomical material (Box 23)
      - 1855-1861 (Box 23)
      - 1862-1868 (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 25)
    - Weather synopses and probabilities (Box 26)
    - 1871 (Box 26)
    - 1872 (Box 27)
    - Weather maps, 1870 (Box 28 (oversize))
    - Certificates and awards (Box 29 (oversize))
    - Miscellaneous (Box 30-31)
- Speech and Article File (Box 32)
  Drafts and printed copies of speeches, articles, reports and autobiographical writings.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Speeches (Box 32)
  - Articles (Box 32)
  - Annual reports (Box 32)
  - Autobiographical writings (Box 32)
- Printed Matter (Box 33-34)
  Newspaper clippings and miscellaneous printed matter.
  - General (Box 33)
  - General (Box 34)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 34)